in this video we're going to talk about
redis and how redis can be used as a
primary database for complex
applications that need to store data in
multiple formats first we will see what
redis is and its usages as well as
why it is suitable for modern complex
microservice applications we will talk
about how redi supports storing multiple
data formats for different purposes
through its modules next we will see how
redis as an in-memory database can
persist data and recover from data loss
we'll also talk about how redis
optimizes memory storage cost using
redis on flash
then we will see very interesting use
cases of scaling readies and replicating
it across multiple geographic regions
and finally since one of the most
popular platforms for running
microservices is kubernetes and since
running stateful applications in
kubernetes is a bit challenging we will
see how you can easily run redis on
kubernetes i'm proud to say that i have
partnered up with redis to make this
video so big thanks to redis for
sponsoring and making this video
possible
now first of all redis which actually
stands for remote dictionary server is
an in-memory database
so many people have used it as a cache
on top of other databases to improve the
application performance however what
many people don't know is that redis is
a fully fledged primary database that
can be used to store and persist
multiple data formats for complex
applications let's see the use cases and
examples for that let's look at a common
setup for a microservices application
let's say we have a complex social media
application with millions of users and
let's say our microservices application
uses a relational database like mysql to
store the data
in addition because we are collecting
tons of data daily we have an
elasticsearch database for fast
filtering and searching the data
now the users are all connected to each
other so we need a graph database to
represent these connections
plus our application has a lot of media
content that users share with each other
daily
and for that we have a document database
and finally for a better performance for
the application we have a cache service
that caches the data from other
databases and makes it accessible faster
now it's obvious that this is a pretty
complex setup but let's see what are the
challenges of this setup
first of all all these data services
need to be deployed run and maintained
right this means your team needs to have
some kind of knowledge on how to
operate all these data services
plus of course for high availability and
better performance you would want to
scale your services and each of these
data services scales differently has
different infrastructure requirements
and that could be an additional
challenge so overall using multiple data
services for your application increases
the effort of maintaining your whole
application setup of course as an easier
alternative to running and managing the
services yourself you can use the
managed data services from cloud
providers but this could be very
expensive because on cloud platforms you
pay for each managed data service
separately
now on the development side your
application code also gets pretty
complex because you need to talk to
multiple data services and for each
service you would need a separate
connector and separate logic and this of
course makes testing your applications
also quite challenging
and finally the more number of services
that talk to each other the higher the
latency because even though each service
may be fast on its own
each connection step between the
services or each network hub will add
some latency to your application
in comparison with a multi-modal
database like redis you resolve most of
these challenges first of all you run
and maintain just one data service so
your application also needs to talk to a
single data store and that requires only
one programmatic interface for that data
service and latency will be reduced by
going to a single data endpoint and
eliminating
several internal network hubs so having
one database like redis that allows you
to store different types of data or
basically allows you to have multiple
types of databases in one as well as act
as a cache solves such challenges
so let's see how redis actually works
first of all how does ready support
multiple data formats in a single
database
the way it works is that you have ready
score which is a key value store that
already supports storing multiple types
of data and then you can extend that
core with what's called modules for
different data types which your
application needs for different purposes
so for example ready search for search
functionality like elasticsearch or
redis graph for graph data storage and
so on and a great thing about this is
that it's modular so these different
types of database functionalities are
not tightly integrated into one database
as in many other multi-modal databases
but rather you can pick and choose
exactly which data service functionality
you need for your application
and then basically add that module and
of course when using redis as a primary
database you don't need an additional
cache because you have that
automatically out of the box with redis
that means again less complexity in your
application
because you don't need to implement
the logic for managing populating and
invalidating cache and finally as an
in-memory database redis is of course
super fast and performant which of
course makes the application itself
faster but in addition it also makes
running the application tests way faster
as well because radius doesn't need a
schema like other databases so it
doesn't need time to initialize the
database and build the schema and so on
before running the tests so you can
start with an empty redis database every
time and generate data for tests as you
need and fast tests can really increase
your development productivity
okay great so we understood how redis
works and all its benefits but at this
point you may be wondering how can an
in-memory database persist data because
if the redis process or the server on
which redis is running fails all the
data in memory is gone right and if i
lose the data how can i recover it so
basically how can i be confident that my
data is safe well the simplest way to
have data backups is by replicating
redis so if the redis master instance
goes down the replicas will still be
running and have all the data so if you
have a replicated redis the replicas
will have the data but of course if all
the radius instances go down you will
lose the data because there will be no
replica remaining so we need real
persistence
well redis has multiple mechanisms for
persisting the data and keeping the data
safe first one the snapshots which you
can configure based on time number of
requests etc so snapshots of your data
will be stored on a disk which you can
use to recover your data if the whole
radius database is gone but note that
you will lose the last minutes of data
because you usually do snapshotting
every five minutes or an hour depending
on your needs so as an alternative redis
uses something called aof which stands
for append only file in this case every
change is saved to the disk for
persistence continuously and when
restarting redis or after an outage
redis will replay the append only file
locks to rebuild the state so aof is
more durable but can be slower than
snapshotting
and of course you can also use a
combination of both aof and snapshots
where the append only file is persisting
data from memory to disk continuously
plus you have regular snapshots in
between to save the data state in case
you need to recover it this means that
even if the redis database itself
or the servers the underlying
infrastructure where redis is running
all fail you still have all your data
safe and you can easily recreate and
restart a new redis database with all
the data
now a very interesting question is
where is that persistent storage so
where is that disk which holds your
snapshots and the append only file locks
located are they on the same servers
where redis is running well this
question actually leads us to the trend
or a best practice of data persistence
in cloud environments which is that it's
always better to separate the servers
that run your application and data
services
from the persistent storage that stores
your data so with a specific example if
your applications and services run in
the cloud on let's say aws ec2 instance
you should use ebs or elastic block
storage to persist your data instead of
storing them on the ec2 instances hard
drive for example because if that ec2
instance died you won't have access to
any of its storage whether it's ram or
disk storage or whatever so if you want
persistence and durability for your data
you must put your data outside the
instances on an external network storage
as a result by separating these two if
the server instance fails or if all the
instances fail you still have the disk
and all the data on it unaffected you
just spin up other instances and take
the data from the ebs and that's it and
this makes your infrastructure way
easier to manage because each server is
equal you don't have any special servers
with any special data or files on it so
you don't care if you lose your whole
infrastructure because you can just
recreate a new one and pull the data
from a separate storage and you're good
to go again
so going back to redis example
ready service will be running on the
servers and using server ram to store
the data
while the append only file logs and
snapshots will be persisted on a disk
outside those servers making your data
more durable
great now we know you can persist data
with redis for durability and recovery
while using ram or memory storage for
great performance and speed
so the question you may have here is
isn't storing data in memory expensive
so you would need more servers compared
to a database that stores data on disk
simply because memory is limited in size
so there's a trade-off between the cost
and performance well redis actually has
a way to optimize this using a service
called redis on flash which is part of
redis enterprise so how does this work
it's a pretty simple concept actually
redison flash extends the rem to the
flash drive or ssd where frequently used
values are stored in rem and the
infrequently used ones are stored on ssd
so for redis it's just more ram on the
server and this means
that redis can use more of the
underlying infrastructure or the
underlying server resources by using
both ram and ssd drive to store the data
increasing the storage capacity on each
server and this way saving you
infrastructure costs
all right so we've talked about data
storage for redis database and how it
all works including the best practices
now another very interesting topic is
how do we scale a redis database
let's say my one oneredice instance runs
out of memory so data becomes too large
to hold in memory or radius becomes a
bottleneck and can't handle any more
requests in such case how do i increase
the capacity
and memory size for my redis database
we have several options for that first
of all ready supports clustering which
means you can have a primary or master
redis instance
which can be used to read and write data
and you can have multiple replicas of
that primary instance for reading the
data this way you can scale red is to
handle more requests and in addition
increase the high availability of your
database because if master fails one of
the replicas can take over and your
radius database basically can continue
functioning without any issues
now these replicas will all hold copies
of the data of the primary instance so
the more replicas you have the more
memory space you need and one server may
not have sufficient memory for all your
replicas plus if you have all the
replicas on one server and that server
fails
your whole radius database is gone and
you will have a downtime instead you
want to distribute these replicas among
multiple nodes or servers so for example
your master instance will be on one node
and two replicas on other two nodes
well that seems good enough
but what if your data set grows too
large to fit in a memory on a single
server plus we have scaled the reads in
the database so all the requests that
basically just query the data but our
master instance is still alone and still
has to handle all the rights so what is
the solution here for that we use the
concept of sharding which is a general
concept in databases and which redis
also supports
so sharding basically means that you
take your complete data set and divide
it into smaller chunks or subsets of
data where each shard is responsible for
its own subset of data
so that means instead of having one
master instance that handles all the
writes to the complete data set
you can split it into let's say four
shards
each of them responsible for reads and
writes to a subset of the data and each
shard also needs less memory capacity
because they just have a fourth of the
data
this means you can distribute and run
charts on smaller nodes and basically
scale your cluster horizontally and of
course as your data set grows and as you
need even more resources you can reshart
your radius database which basically
means you just
split your data in even smaller chunks
and create more shards
so having multiple nodes which run
multiple replicas of redis which are all
sharded gives you a very performant
highly available redis database that can
handle much more requests without
creating any bottlenecks now i have to
note here that this setup is great but
of course you would need to manage it
yourself do the scaling add notes do the
sharding and then resharting etc so for
some teams that are more focused on the
application development and more
business logic rather than running and
maintaining data services this could be
a lot of unwanted effort so as an easier
alternative in redis enterprise you get
this kind of setup automatically because
the scaling sharding and so on is all
managed for you
now let's consider another interesting
scenario for applications that need even
higher availability and performance
across multiple geographic locations so
let's say we have this replicated
sharded redis database cluster in one
region in the data center of london
europe but we have the two following use
cases
first our users are geographically
distributed so they are accessing the
application from all over the world so
we want to distribute our application
and data services globally
close to the users to give our users
better performance and second if the
complete data center in london europe
for example
goes down we want an immediate switch
over to another data center so that the
ready service stays available in other
words we want replicas of the whole
redis cluster in data centers in
multiple geographic locations or regions
this means a single data should be
replicated to many clusters spread
across multiple regions
with each cluster being fully able to
accept reads and writes
so in that case you would have multiple
redis clusters
that will act as local redis instances
in each region and the data will be
synced across these geographically
distributed clusters
this is a feature available in redis
enterprise and is called active active
deployment because you have multiple
active databases in different locations
so with this setup we'll have lower
latency for the users
and even if the redis database in one
region completely goes down the other
regions will be unaffected and if the
connection or syncing between the
regions breaks for a short time because
of some network problem for example
the reddish clusters in these regions
can update the data independently and
once connection is re-established they
can sync up those changes again now of
course when you hear that the first
question that may pop up in your mind is
how does redis resolve the changes in
multiple regions to the same data set so
if the same data changed in multiple
regions how does radies make sure that
data changes of any region isn't lost
and data is correctly synced and how
does it ensure data consistency
specifically for that redis enterprise
uses a concept called crdts which stands
for
conflict-free
replicated data types and this concept
is used to resolve any conflicts
automatically at the database level and
without any data loss so basically redis
itself has a mechanism for merging the
changes which were made to the same data
set from multiple sources in a way that
none of the data changes are lost and
any conflicts are properly resolved and
since as you learned ready supports
multiple data types for each data type
they use its own data conflict
resolution rules which are the most
optimal for that specific data type
so simply put instead of just overriding
the changes of one source
and just discarding all the others all
the parallel changes are kept and
intelligently resolved
and again this is automatically done for
you with this active active
geo-replication feature so you don't
need to worry about that and the last
topic i want to address with redis is
running redis in kubernetes as i said
redis is a great fit for complex
microservices that need to support
multiple data types and that need an
easy scaling of a database without
worrying about data consistency
and we also know that the new standard
for running microservices is the
kubernetes platform so running redis in
kubernetes is a very interesting and
common use case so how does that work
with open source redis you can deploy
replicated redis as a help chart or
kubernetes manifest files and basically
using the replication and scaling rules
that we already talked about
set up and run a highly available redis
database
the only difference would be that the
hosts where redis will run will be
kubernetes pods instead of for example
ec2 instances or any other
physical or virtual servers but the same
sharding replicating and scaling
concepts apply here as well when you
want to run redis cluster in kubernetes
and you would basically have to manage
that setup yourself
however as i mentioned many teams don't
want to have the effort of maintaining
these third-party services because they
rather invest their time and resources
in application development or other
tasks so having an easier alternative is
important here as well so redis
enterprise has a managed redis cluster
which you can deploy as a kubernetes
operator if you don't know operators
operator in kubernetes is basically a
concept where you can bundle all the
resources
needed to operate a certain application
or service so that you don't have to
manage it yourself or you don't have to
operate it yourself
so instead of a human operating a
database you basically have all this
logic in an automated form to operate a
database for you and many databases have
operators for kubernetes and each such
operator has of course its own logic
based on who wrote them and how they
wrote them
the redis enterprise on kubernetes
operator specifically
automates deployment and configuration
of the whole radius database in your
kubernetes cluster it also takes care of
scaling doing the backups and recovering
the redis cluster if needed etc so it
takes over the complete operation of
radius cluster inside the kubernetes
cluster well i hope you learned a lot in
this video and that i was able to answer
many of your questions if you want to
try redis enterprise cloud be sure to
check out my special link in the video
description for a 200 credit and if you
want to learn more similar technologies
and concepts then make sure to subscribe
to my channel because i make videos
regularly about different devops and
cloud technologies also comment below if
you have any questions regarding reddis
or any new topic suggestions and with
that thank you for watching and see you
in the next video